The Charles Martin Loeffler Collection
Yale University Music Library
The Charles Martin Loeffler Collection
1895-1936
Misc. Ms. 270
Yale University Music Library
3
(2 boxes)
The Charles Martin Loeffler Collection contains sketches, manuscript scores, and printed editions of 23 musical compositions by the Alsatian-American composer Charles Martin Loeffler (1861-1935)
Loeffler, Charles Martin, 1861-1935
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles Martin Loeffler Collection was established in the Music Library of Yale University by Louis Krasner in 1975.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: I. Music by Charles Martin Loeffler. II. Music by others. III. Miscellaneous items.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Martin Loeffler Collection contains sketches, manuscript scores, and printed editions of 23 of Loeffler's musical compositions, including operas, choral works, songs, and chamber music. The Collection also holds: arrangements by Loeffler of other composers' music; 1 photograph of Loeffler; and 1 letter from Carl Engel to Loeffler, dated December 10, 1928.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Martin Loeffler was born on January 30, 1861. His place of birth is disputed; he claimed to be Alsatian, but according to his biographer Ellen Knight, documents indicate that he was actually born near Berlin. He studied violin and composition in Germany (where Joseph Joachim was one of his teachers) and France, and in 1881 he went to the United States, which eventually became his permanent home. From 1882 to 1903 Loeffler was Second Concertmaster of the Boston Symphony Orchestra, and he achieved considerable renown as a solo violinist. He composed extensively, and his works were widely performed during his lifetime. He received many awards, including an honorary doctorate from Yale University in 1926. Charles Martin Loeffler died on May 19, 1935.
Composers -- Correspondence; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Operas -- Scores; Songs; Viola d'amore and piano music -- Scores and parts; Violin and piano music -- Scores and parts; Engel, Carl, 1883-1944; Loeffler, Charles Martin, 1861-1935
- Register (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Music by Charles Martin Loeffler, Series I
  - [Beat! Beat! Drums!] Beat! Beat! Drums!: for men's voices in unison / words by Walt Whitman; music by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- Boston: C.C. Birchard, c1932., 1 score (13 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    For unison men's voices and piano.
    English words.
    Pl. no.: 1548
  - [Canticum Fratris Solis] Canticum Fratris Solis / Charles Martin Loeffler; set for voice and chamber orchestra to the hymn of St. Francis of Assisi; in a modern Italian version by Gino Perera -- Washington, D.C.: The Library of Congress, c1929., 1 score (95 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Inscribed in ink: "To Mrs. Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge in profound admiration. Ch. M. Loeffler."
    Bookplate: The gift of The Library of Congress (Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation) to Elise Fay Loeffler. No. 78 of an edition limited to 200 copies.
  - [Cynthia] Cynthia / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript part (7 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Holograph in ink.
    Far violin and piano.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Cynthia manuscript #1.
    Frames 1-6
  - [Cynthia] Cynthia / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript score (12 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For violin and piano.
    Corrections in pencil.
    At end: Medfield Winter 1926.
    Title, composer, and dedication to Richard P. Strong, M.D, crossed out.
    Knight inventory, p. 1, Cynthia manuscript #2.
    Frames 7-18
  - [Cynthia] Cynthia / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript part (4 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Incomplete: 20 measures not filled in.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Cynthia manuscript #3.
    Frames 19-22
  - [Cynthia] Cynthia / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Incomplete: Opening measures not filled in.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Cynthia manuscript #4.
    Frames 23-30
  - [Cynthia] Cynthia, 1 manuscript score (9 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    At end: 1926 Medfield Mass.
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 1-2.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Cynthia manuscript #5.
    Frames 31-37
  - [Divertimento, violin, orchestra, arr.] Divertimento für Violine mit Begleitung grossen Orchesters / von Ch. M. Loeffler; Übertragung des Orchesters für Klavier von Heinrich Gebhard., 1 score (35 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Copyist's manuscript in ink.
    Corrections in pencil and pasted in.
    Acc. arr. for piano.
    Contents: Preamble -- Eklogue -- Nouvelles variations sur le thème Dies Irae.
    Frames 38-74
  - Eery moonlight (Box 1, Folder 9)
    See [Norske land, revised]
  - [Evocation] Evocation: on lines from the Select epigrams of Greek anthology by J.W. Mackail: for women's voices and modern orchestra / by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- Boston: Published by C.C. Birchard & Company for The Juilliard Foundation, c1932., 1 miniature score (47 p.); 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    For chorus (SSAA) and orchestra.
    Pl. no.: 1527
  - [Fantasia (Sketches)] Fantasia, 6 manuscript p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Holograph in pencil.
    For cello and piano?
    Incomplete: Lacks p. l-2.
    Frames 75-78
  - Fiddler of Dooney (Box 1, Folder 11)
    See [Irish fantasies. Fiddler of Dooney]
  - Host of the air (Box 1, Folder 11)
    See [Irish fantasies. Host of the air]
  - Hosting of the Sidhe (Box 1, Folder 11)
    See [Irish fantasies. Hosting of the Sidhe]
  - [Irish fantasies. Fiddler of Dooney] The fiddler of Dooney / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript score (16 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    For voice and piano.
    Text by W.B. Yeats.
    No. 3 of Five Irish fantasies.
    Frames 79-89
  - [Irish fantasies. Host of the air] The host of the air / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript score (12 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    No. 2 of Five Irish fantasies.
    At end: Medfield Summer 1907. Published by Schirmer in 1908.
    Frames 90-101
  - [Irish fantasies. Hosting of the Sidhe] The hosting of the Sidhe / Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    "To T.R. Fay."
    No. 1 of Five Irish fantasies.
    At end: Medfield Summer 1907.
    Frames 102-109
  - Der Kehraus (Box 1, Folder 14)
    See [Vereinsamt]
  - [Melodie de Ole Bull] Melodie de Ole Bull, 1 score (1 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Incomplete: Lacks all after measure 14.
    Frame 110
  - [Memories of my childhood] Memories of my childhood: life in a Russian village: poem for modern orchestra / by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1925., 1 score (51 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes program note.
    Pl. no.: 32027c
  - [Mescolanza "Olla Podrida"] Mescolanza Olla Podrida, 1 manuscript score (13 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    For viola d'amore and piano.
    Knight inventory p. 2, Mescolanza manuscript #1.
    Frame 111-123
  - [Mescolanza "Olla Podrida"] Mescolanza, 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Incomplete.
    Knight inventory p. 2, Mescolanza manuscript #2.
    Frames 124-129
  - [Mescolanza "Olla Podrida"] Mescolanzia "Olla Podrida"; Spanish tunes., 1 manuscript score (9 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Knight inventory p. 2, Mescolanza manuscript #3.
    Frames 130-138
  - [Mescolanza "Olla Podrida"], 1 score (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Holograph in pencil and ink.
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 1-4, and all after p. 11.
    Frames 139-145
  - [Mort de Tintagiles, arr.] La mort de Tintagiles: poème dramatique d'après le drame de M. Meaterlinck: pour grand orchestre et viole d'amour / Ch. M. Loeffler: réduction pour piano à 4 mains par Marcel Labey. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1908., 1 score (39 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Arr. for piano 4 hands.
    "Opus-6."
    Includes program note by Philip Hale.
    Pl. no.: 19317c
  - [Musique] Musique pour 2 violons, alto et violoncelle; pour les Flonzaleys / Ch. M. Loeffler. -- 1917-18., 1 manuscript score (16 + 10 + 12 p.); 23 x 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    On cover: To the memory of Victor Chapman, aviation near Verdun.
    Contents: Musique -- Le saint pour les Paques -- Finale: à vol d'oisseau.
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 1-2 of 2nd movement.
    Frames 146-184
  - [Norske land] Norske land, 1 manuscript score (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Knight inventory p. 1, Norske land manuscript #1.
    Frames 185-195
  - [Norske land] Allegretto, 1 manuscript score (9 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Frames 196-202
  - [Norske land] Norske land, 1 manuscript score (6 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Knight inventory p. 1, Norske land manuscript #2.
    Frames 203-208
  - [Norske land (Sketches)] 2 mélodies norvégiennes / paraphrase par Ch. M. Loeffler, 1 manuscript leaf; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    On verso: Holograph part for Cynthia, incomplete.
    Frames 209-210
  - [Norske land. Revised as Eery moonlight (Sketches)], 4 manuscript p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    For violin or viola d'amore and piano.
    Frames 211-214
  - [Norske saga] Norske saga; divertissement pour contrebasse et piano d'après deux motifs norvégiens et un ranz des vaches, tires de la Collection Nationale de Warmuth, Christiania / par Ch. M. Loeffler., 1 manuscript part (4 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Holograph, signed, in ink.
    Corrections in ink pasted in.
    Revision of Norske land.
    On cover: A monsieur Serge Koussevitzky, humble marque de profonde admiration pour le grand artiste, sincère affection aussi pour le grand homme.
    Title page crossed out.
    At end: Medfield 20 Avril 1929.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Norske sage manuscript #1.
    Frames 215-219
  - [Norske saga] Norske saga, 1 manuscript score (12 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    For double bass and piano.
    Corrections in pencil and ink pasted in.
    Incomplete: Lacks pp. 7-10.
    Knight inventory p. 1, Norske saga manuscript #2.
    Frames 220-227
  - [Norske saga] Lento, 1 manuscript part (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    For double bass.
    Revision of Norske Land.
    Frames 228-231
  - [Norske saga, arr.], 1 manuscript score (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    For viola d'amore, double bass, and piano.
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 1-6.
    Frames 232-236
  - [Norske saga, arr. (Sketches)] Lento, 1 manuscript score (14 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Frames 237-250
  - [Ode] Ode: for one who fell in battle / words by F.W. Parsons; music by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1911., 1 score (19 p.); 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    For chorus (SSAATTBB) unaccompanied.
    Pl. no.: 22365
  - Olla Podrida (Box 1, Folder 33)
    See [Mescolanza "Olla Podrida"]
  - [Oriental ditty] Oriental ditty on a delightful tune by Myers, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    For violin and piano?
    Knight inventory p. 3, Oriental ditty manuscript #1.
    Frames 251-252
  - [Oriental ditty] Sur un air délicieux de Myers, 1 manuscript score (1 leaf); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    For violin-and piano?
    Frames 253-254
  - [Oriental ditty (Sketches)] Oriental ditty on a tune by Myers, 1 manuscript score (1 p.); 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Holograph in ink and pencil.
    Knight inventory p. 3. Oriental ditty manuscript #3.
    Frames 255
  - [Pagan poem] A pagan poem after Virgil: composed for orchestra with piano, English horn and three trumpets obligato, Op. 14 / by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1909., 1 score (107 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    On title page: To Elise in deep affection,
    Martin, Nov. 1909.
    No. 3 of an edition of 15 copies printed for the composer on Van Gelder hand-made paper.
  - [Passion of Hilarion] The passion of Hilarion: an opera in one act and two tableaux after a play by William Sharp / by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- [Boston]: C.C. Birchard, c1936., 1 score (278 p.); 49 cm. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Italian and English words.
    Photocopy of composer's manuscript.
  - [Poem] Poem / composed for orchestra by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Shirmer, c1923., 1 score (60 p.): 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Pl. no.: 31382
  - [Psalm 137] Psalm CXXXVII: by the waters of Babylon, for four-part chorus of women's voices with accompaniment of organ, harp, two flutes, and violoncello obligato, op. 3 / by Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1907., 1 score (22 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    No. 2 of an edition of 5 copies printed on Van Gelder hand-made paper.
    Pl. no.: 19452
  - [Vereinsamt] Vereinsamt. Der Kehraus, 1 manuscript score (12 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    German words.
    Texts by F. Nietzsche, J. von Eichendorff.
    Frames 256-269
  - [Vereinsamt] Vereinsamt. Der Kehraus, 1 manuscript score (10 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Incomplete: Lacks all after p. 10.
    Frames 270-276
  - [Vereinsamt] Vereinsamt, 1 manuscript score (5 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Text by F. Nietzsche.
    Frames 277-281
  - [Vereinsamt] [Der Kehraus], 1 manuscript score (7 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Text by F. von Eichendorff.
    Frames 282-288
  - [Villanelle du diable] La villanelle du diable: d'après un poème de M. Rollinat: fantaisie symphonique pour grand orchestre et orgue, op. 9 / composée par Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1905., 1 score (84 p.); 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    No. 1 of 10 copies printed for the author on Van Gelder hand-made paper.
    Pl. no.: 17535
  - [Villanelle du diable] La villanelle du diable: d'après un poème de M. Rollinat: fantasie symphonique pour grand orchestre et orgue, op. 9 / composée par Ch. M. Loeffler. -- New York: G. Schirmer, c1908., 1 score (33 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Arr. for piano 4 hands by Marcel Labey.
    Pl. no.: 19430c
  - [Violin studies], 10 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Frames 337-350
  - [Zapateado (Sketches)] Zapateado, 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Frames 289-290
  - [Unidentified fragment], 1 manuscript score (9 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    In 3 movements.
    Incomplete: Lacks opening p., not finished.
    Frames 291-299.
  - [Unidentified sketches], 6 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Frames 300-305
- Music by others, Series II
  - [Französische Suiten. Nr. 5. Courante, arr.] Courante, Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750; 1 manuscript score (1 leaf); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Copyist's manuscript in pencil.
    Arr. for violin and piano.
    Arr. by Loeffler, in his hand.
    Frames 306-307
  - [Romances, violin, orchestra, op. 40, G major, arr.], Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827; 1 manuscript score; 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Copyist's manuscript-in ink.
    In Loeffler's hand.
    Incomplete: Lacks all but 3 measures.
    Frames 308
  - [Shylock. Vocal score] Shylock, op. 57 / comédie en 3 actes de Edmond Haraucourt d'après Shakespeare; musique de scène de Gabriel Fauré. -- Paris: J. Hamelle, [n.d.], Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924; 1 vocal score (27 p.); 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Acc. arr. for piano by Gustave Samazeuilh.
    Contents: Prélude et chanson -- Entr'acte -- Madrigal -- Épithalame -- Nocturne -- Final.
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 11-18.
  - [Shylock. Nocturne] Nocturne / G. Fauré., Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    13 manuscript parts; various sizes.
    For vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db.
    Frames 309-327
  - [Shylock. Nocturne, arr.] Nocturne from incidental music to Shylock / Gabriel Fauré., Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924; 1 score (2 p.) + 2 parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Arr. for viole d'amore, violoncello, and piano.
    Frames 328-331
  - [Sonatas, harpsichord, K. 113, A major, arr.] Allegrissimo / Domenico Scarlatti., Scarlatti, Domenico, 1685-1757; 1 manuscript score (5 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Frames 332-336
- Miscellaneous items, Series III
  - 1 photograph of Charles Martin Loeffler (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 1 letter from Carl Engel to Charles Martin Loeffler, December 10, 1928, regarding Loeffler's Canticum Fratris Solis (Box 2, Folder 56)